Finding Aid for the Ruth St. Denis Papers LSC.1031
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ruth St. Denis papers
1880-1968
UCLA Library Special Collections
St. Denis, Ruth
LSC.1031
79.2 linear feet (157 boxes, 8 cartons, and 17 flat boxes)
Ruth St. Denis (1879-1968) was a modern dance pioneer who combined spirituality and dance. Throughout her career, St. Denis's dances were greatly influenced by eastern culture and religion. In the later years of her career, Christian themes were also explored and depicted in her works. Her papers include handwritten journals, personal and professional correspondence, essays, poems, lectures, choreographic notes, musical scores, dance programs and ephemera, photographic prints, reel-to-reel audio recordings, books from her personal library, and business materials. The collection spans the majority of her life, though the bulk of collection derives from the 1920s to her death in 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Seven envelopes of negatives in Box 153, Folder 11 unvailable due to damaged condition.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Ruth St. Denis, purchase, 1966.
Brother St. Denis, purchase, 1968.
Gift of Buzz St. Denis, 1969.
Catherine Barnes, purchase, 1987.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9932222453606533
Biography
Ruth St. Denis (1879-1968) was a modern dance pioneer who combined spirituality and dance. Throughout her career, St. Denis's dances were greatly influenced by eastern culture and religion. In the later years of her career, Christian themes were also explored and depicted in her works. Born Ruth Dennis in New Jersey, she later added "St." as part of her stage name. St. Denis's training began as a child, with the practice of physical exercises developed by François Delsarte. This greatly influenced her future style of dance. As a teenager, she appeared in Broadway musicals and was a protégé of David Belasco. Inspired by a poster advertising Egyptian Deities Cigarettes with an image of the Egyptian goddess Iris, St. Denis began choreographing dances that expressed the goddess's mysticism. The first dance piece that brought her into the circuit of higher art was Radha, which she first performed in 1906. This dance portrayed the story of Krishna and his love for a mortal maid. St. Denis's intention was to create a work that would serve as a spiritual expression of eastern cultural themes.
In 1914, St. Denis married her dance partner, Ted Shawn. The following year, they founded the Denishawn School of Dance in Los Angeles, California, one of the first schools devoted to "aesthetic dancing." In 1920, the school moved to New York City. Aesthetic dancing involved spiritual, natural movements. Some of Denishawn's illustrious pupils were Martha Graham, Doris Humphrey, Charles Weidman, and Louise Brooks, the future film star. The Denishawn dancers toured Asia for fifteen months in 1925, performing dances inspired by Asian and Egyptian cultures.
In 1927, St. Denis founded the Society of Spiritual Arts, focusing on the religious aspects of dance. In 1931, St. Denis and Shawn separated maritally, but did not legally divorce. Though they dissolved Denishawn, St. Denis remained close to Shawn throughout her career. In 1934, St. Denis founded the Church of Divine Dance at her studio in Los Angeles, which, like the Society of Spiritual Arts, established dance as a means of worship. Here, she led dance masses and rituals. In 1938, she founded the first college dance program in an American university at Adelphi University in New York State.
St. Denis died of a heart attack in Hollywood, California in 1968. As a pivotal figure of modern dance, she left behind an esteemed legacy and several dance companies have honored her by performing her pieces. She was inducted into the National Museum of Dance's Mr. & Mrs. Cornelius Vanderbilt Whitney Hall of Fame in 1987, and was among the first to be distinguished by the Dance Heritage Coalition in its America's Irreplaceable Dance Treasures http://www.danceheritage.org/treasures.html.
Scope and Content
This collection is comprised of the personal papers of Ruth St. Denis. It includes St. Denis's handwritten journals, which begin at the turn of the century and continue until weeks before her death, personal and professional correspondence, essays, poems, lectures, choreographic notes, musical scores, dance programs and ephemera, photographic prints, reel-to-reel audio recordings, books from her personal library, and business materials. The collection spans the majority of her life, though the bulk of collection derives from the 1920s to her death in 1968.
Organization and Arrangement
Series 1: Journals, 1900s-1968
Series 2: Correspondence, 1886-1968
Subseries 2.1: List of contacts
Subseries 2.2: Greeting cards
Subseries 2.3: Correspondence, 1886-1968
Series 3: Writings, 1900s-1968
Subseries 3.1: Essays and manuscripts, 1910s-1960s
Subseries 3.2: Poems, 1910s-1960s
Subseries 3.3: Lectures and speeches, 1930s-1960s
Subseries 3.4: Writings of others, 1910s-1960s
Subseries 3.5: Inventories of writings, 1920s-1960s
Series 4: Performance and dance materials, 1910s-1960s
Subseries 4.1: Choreography and performance note, 1910s-1960s
Subseries 4.2: Performance research/resources, 1910s-1960s
Subseries 4.3: Education and dance center materials, 1940s-1960s
Subseries 4.4: Sheet music, 1920s-1960s
Series 5: Media, 1900s-1960s
Subseries 5.1: Photographs, 1900s-1960s
Subseries 5.2: Negatives
Subseries 5.3: Reel to reel audio recordings, 1950s-1960s
Series 6: Clippings, ephemera, and publications, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 6.1: Clippings and publications, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 6.2: Ephemera, 1920s-1960s
Series 7: Books from personal library
Series 8: Business materials, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 8.1: Financial materials, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 8.2: Medical materials, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 8.3: Legal materials, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 8.4: Business notes and memos, 1920s-1960s
Subseries 8.5: Lists and inventories, 1920s-1960s
Series are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Reflections on a life in the dance. Ruth St. Denis, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1965. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Elyse Robert collection on Ruth St. Denis, 1932-1991 (Collection 1735). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Ruth St. Denis Collection. Adelphi University Archives and Special Collections, Garden City, NY.
Photograph Collection on Ruth St. Denis. MS-P070. Special Collections and Archives, The UC Irvine Libraries, Irvine, California.
Choreographers -- California, Southern -- Archives.; Diaries.; Women dancers -- California, Southern -- Archives.; St. Denis, Ruth -- Archives
- Series 1: Journals, 1900s-1968
  Scope and Content
  The journals series contains bound journals and loose journal entries that were written throughout St. Denis's life, from the early 1900s to 1968 a few weeks before she passed away. These journals include such topics as St. Denis' performances, choreographic concepts, religious and aesthetic views, community and social problems, travels, personal life, and public image as an artist. Her journals provide insight into the struggles she faced towards the end of her career when St. Denis did not have the financial stability to perform what she wanted and as often as she wanted.
  - Journals in notebook, "1925 Orient," "3-96," Holograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journals in notebooks, "1900-1909" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journals in notebooks, "No. I copy/Typed", 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journal entries, 1910s; Folder contains a bound leather notebook in delicate condition, handle with care. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Journal entries, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1924 Autumn-1928 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes Journal Written In Theatres
  - Journals in notebooks, "1928 #2" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Journals in notebooks, "April 18, 1928," "1928 #1" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1924 Jan-1924 Sept (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes notes on "Dance of the Divine Self"
  - Journals in notebooks, "Journal pages copies '17 '19", circa 1917-1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Journals, 1925 Jan-1925 Nov (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Journals- Diary of Asia Tour 1925-1926 (unidentified writer) (1 of 2), 1925 Aug 7-1926 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Journals- Diary of Asia Tour 1925-1926 (unidentified writer) (2 of 2), 1925 Aug 7-1926 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1927 Nov 9-1929 Feb 19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1927 Nov 9-1929 Feb 19 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Journals, 1928 Mar 31-1928 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Journals- Road Hotel Book, 1928 April-1928 May (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1928 May 25-17 Dec 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1928 May 25-17 Dec 1928 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1929 Jan 1-1929 Dec 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes notes for "Extacy."
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1929 Jan 1-1929 Dec 30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1929 Mar 29-1929 July 4 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1929 Mar 29-1929 July 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1929 July 5-1929 Aug 6 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1929 July 5-1929 Aug 6 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1929 Feb 20-1930 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1929 Feb 20-1930 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1929 Feb 20-1930 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1929 Aug 6-1931 Sep 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes notes for "Incense Dance."
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1929 Aug 6-1931 Sep 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1929 Sept 30-1929 Dec 18 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes sketches.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1929 Sept 30-1929 Dec 18 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1930 May 15-1930 June 13 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes notes for "Temple."
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1930 May 15-1930 June 13 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Journal entries, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Journal entries, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1930 Feb 3-1930 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1930 Feb 3-1930 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1930 June 12-1930 Aug 29 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1930 June 12-1930 Aug 29 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1930 July 3-1930 Sept 25 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1930 July 3-1930 Sept 25 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1957 June 15-1957 June 16 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Journals- undated miscellaneous letters (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Journals (1 of 4), 1930 Sept-1940 Sept (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Includes biographical and war-related writings and notes for "Dance of Death."
  - Journals (2 of 4), 1930 Sept-1940 Sept (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Journals (3 of 4), 1930 Sept-1940 Sept (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Journals (4 of 4), 1930 Sept-1940 Sept (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1931 Feb 15-1931 June 13 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1931 Feb 15-1931 June 13 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1931 Feb 22-1931 Oct 23 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1931 Feb 22-1931 Oct 23 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1931 Nov-1932 Jan (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1931 Nov-1932 Jan (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1932 Jan 5-1932 June 8 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes biographical writings.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1932 Jan 5-1932 June 8 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1932 Jan 5-1932 Dec 31 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Includes biographical writings and poetry.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1932 Jan 5-1932 Dec 31 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1932 Jan 5-1932 Dec 31 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1932 Jan 11 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1932 June 4-1933 Jan 18 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1932 June 4-1933 Jan 18 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1932 June 4-1933 Jan 18 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1933 Jan 1-1933 Aug 28 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1933 Jan 1-1933 Aug 28 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1933 Sept 2-1933 Nov 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1933 Sept 2-1933 Nov 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Journals, 1933 Nov 3-1933 Dec 31 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1934 Jan 1-1934 Feb 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1934 June 2-1934 July 31 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1934 June 2-1934 July 31 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Journals- Odd pages, 1934 Jan 2-1935 June 29 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Includes poems and dance treatment.
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1934 Feb 4-1934 May 30 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes drawings.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1934 Feb 4-1934 May 30 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1934 Aug 28-1934 Nov 18 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Includes notes in French, poems, and speeches.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1934 Aug 28-1934 Nov 18 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1934 Aug 8-1934 Oct 15 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Includes notes for Temple, notes in French.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1934 Aug 8-1934 Oct 15 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Journals- Temple material, 1934 Nov 18-1935 Jan 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1931 Sept-1936 Oct (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Includes biographical writings and notes for Temple.
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1935 Jan, 1935 May 3-1935 Aug 19 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Includes poems.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1935 Jan, 1935 May 3-1935 Aug 19 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Journals, 1935 Jan 1-1935 July 27 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1935 Jan 10-1935 Dec 30 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Includes notes for Temple.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1935 Jan 10-1935 Dec 30 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1935 Feb 3-1935 Mar 25 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1935 Mar 29-1935 June 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1935 Mar 29-1935 June 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Journals, 1935 Aug 25-1935 Sept 25, 1945 Nov (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Journals- Pittsburgh (1 of 2), 1935 Feb-Dec 8; 1935 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence and biographical writings.
  - Journals- Pittsburgh (2 of 2), 1935 Feb-Dec 8; 1935 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Journals- Pittsburgh, 1935 Sep 1-Oct 17 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Journals, 1936 Jan 2-1936 Dec 11 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1936 Jan 2-1937 Jan 15 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1936 Jan 2-1937 Jan 15 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1936 Jan 5-1936 July 28 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Journals, 1936 July 19-1936 Nov 21 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Includes London journals.
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1937 Jan-1937 Dec; 1937 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Includes travel itineraries.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1937 Jan-1937 Dec; 1937 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Journals (1 of 4), 1929-1937; 1937 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Includes notes for costumes, poems (some in French), correspondence, and writings on the New Temple.
  - Journals (2 of 4), 1929-1937; 1937 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Journals (3 of 4), 1929-1937; 1937 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Journals (4 of 4), 1929-1937; 1937 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Journals, 1936-1944; 1936 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Includes poems and religious writings.
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1936 April 1-1936 July 23 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1936 April 1-1936 July 23 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Journals- Unidentified manuscript (1 of 2), 1936 June 25-1936 July 22 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Includes notes for Egyptian Series.
  - Journals- Unidentified manuscript (2 of 2), 1936 June 25-1936 July 22 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1937 Jan 2-1938 Jan 1 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Includes notes for book and biographical writings.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1937 Jan 2-1938 Jan 1 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1936 May 4-1938 Oct 7; 1936 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Includes notes for Temple and correspondence.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1936 May 4-1938 Oct 7; 1936 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1936 May 4-1938 Oct 7; 1936 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Journal- Pearl, 1937 Feb-1951 Mar (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1938 Jan-1938 Dec (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Includes biographical writings, notes for book, and correspondence.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1938 Jan-1938 Dec (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1938 Jan 3-1939 April 16 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Includes notes for book and correspondence.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1938 Jan 3-1939 April 16 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1938 Feb-1938 Nov (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Includes biographical writings and notes for book.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1938 Feb-1938 Nov (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Journals, 1938 Mar-1938 Dec (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1938 Nov 2-1939 June 11 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Includes notes for Adelphi College and correspondence.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1938 Nov 2-1939 June 11 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1939 Jan 2-1939 Dec 30 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence, writings on Moral Re-Armament.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1939 Jan 2-1939 Dec 30 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1939 April 29-1939 Dec 31 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1939 April 29-1939 Dec 31 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1940 Oct-1943 Dec; 1942 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1940 Oct-1943 Dec; 1942 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Journals- On Tour (1 of 3), 1941 Jan 8-1941 Dec 10 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence, biographical writings, writings on war, notes for Temple, and notes for "Babylon" and other dances.
  - Journals- On Tour (2 of 3), 1941 Jan 8-1941 Dec 10 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Journals- On Tour (3 of 3), 1941 Jan 8-1941 Dec 10 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1942 Jan 4-1942 July 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1942 Jan 4-1942 July 2 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1942 Jan-1944 Dec; 1944 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Includes notes for Temple, speeches, drafts for programs, and sketches.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1942 Jan-1944 Dec; 1944 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1942 Jan-1944 Dec; 1944 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1942 July 4-1942 Aug 18 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1943 Jan-1943 Nov (Box 14, Folder 10)
    Includes notes for Temple, and writings on war.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1943 Jan-1943 Nov (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Journals, 1943 Jan-1943 Dec (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1943 Mar 1-1943 Sept 11 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Includes correspondence, writings on war, and notes for "Radha"
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1943 Mar 1-1943 Sept 11 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence, writings on war, and notes for "Radha."
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1943 Mar 1-1943 Sept 11 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Journals- Plant journals, 1943 Aug (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1944 Jan-1944 Dec; 1944 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Includes "The Dialogue Theatre" writings.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1944 Jan-1944 Dec; 1944 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1944 Jan-1944 Dec; 1944 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1944 Nov 1-1944 Dec 31 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1944 Nov 1-1944 Dec 31 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1944 Dec 31-1945 Aug 20 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1944 Dec 31-1945 Aug 20 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Journals, 1945 Jan-1947 Mar; 1945 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    Includes references to Jack Cole.
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1945 July 1-1945 Nov 25 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Includes notes on "Egypta," "Radha," and "The Divine Dance," correspondence, and notes on the studio.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1945 July 1-1945 Nov 25 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1945 July 1-1945 Nov 25 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1945 Nov 6-1945 Dec 31 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1945 Nov 6-1945 Dec 31 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1946 Jan 1-1946 Mar 13 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence.
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1946 Mar 2-1946 Dec 31 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Includes notes for Church of the Divine Dance and correspondence.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1946 Mar 2-1946 Dec 31 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Journals: Phoenix journals, 1946 Mar 6-1946 April 14 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1946 June 14-1946 Oct 27 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Includes notes for "Hindu Dance" and "Egypta," and notes for Temple.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1946 June 14-1946 Oct 27 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1946 June 14-1946 Oct 27 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1944 Jan-1948 Nov; 1948 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Includes ephemera and manuscripts relating to Harro Meller and notes for church of the Divine Dance.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1944 Jan-1948 Nov; 1948 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1946 Nov 5-1946 Dec 22 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1946 Nov 5-1946 Dec 22 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1947 Jan 24-1947 May 1 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1947 Jan 24-1947 May 1 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1947 June 30-1947 July 27 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Includes biographical writings and notes in French.
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1947 Aug 1-1947 Sep 27 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1947 Aug 1-1947 Sep 27 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1947 Sep 28-1947 Nov 25 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    Includes poems by Harro Meller, references to UCLA, and correspondence.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1947 Sep 28-1947 Nov 25 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1947 Jan-1948 May (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence, scripts, and references to Harro Meller.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1947 Jan-1948 May (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1947 May-1947 July (Box 18, Folder 3)
    Includes correspondence and references to Harro Meller.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1947 May-1947 July (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1948 April-1949 April (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Includes poems, correspondence, notes on Church of the Divine Dance, references to Harro Meller, and notes and postcards of Arizona and Nevada.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1948 April-1949 April (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Journal entries, 1957-1968 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1943 Jan-1950 May; 1948-1950 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Includes notes for Temple, correspondence, and references to Harro Meller.
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1943 Jan-1950 May; 1948-1950 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1943 Jan-1950 May; 1948-1950 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1947 Jun-1950 Mar; 1949-1950 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Includes "Dialogue" writings and writings on Shankara.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1947 Jun-1950 Mar; 1949-1950 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1948 Jan-1958 July (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Journals (1 of 3), 1948 Dec-1950 Dec (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Journals (2 of 3), 1948 Dec-1950 Dec (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Journals (3 of 3), 1948 Dec-1950 Dec (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Journals, 1949 June 2-1949 Aug 6 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Journals, 1949 Sept 14-1949 Dec 7 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Includes correspondence, references to Harro Meller, Carnegie Hall, and "White Jade."
  - Journals (1 of 2), 1950 Jan-1951 Mar; 1950-1951 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Includes notes on School of the Silent Dance and dissolution of the RSD Foundation.
  - Journals (2 of 2), 1950 Jan-1951 Mar; 1950-1951 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Journals, 1951 Nov 24-1951 Dec 20 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Journals- Complete 1932 Journal, 1932 Jan 5-1932 Dec 31 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Journals (1 of 4), 1946-1952; 1952 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Includes references to UCLA, death of St. Denis' mother, notes for "Dances of Healing" and "The Sacred Dances," and Paramount journals.
  - Journals (2 of 4), 1946-1952; 1952 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Journals (3 of 4), 1946-1952; 1952 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Journals (4 of 4), 1946-1952; 1952 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1959 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Journals, 1950s (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1956-1961 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Journal entries, 1959 Jan-1959 Mar (Box 20, Folder 10)